Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammā
sambuddhassa I send greetings and best
wishes to everyone and I hope that
everybody in these very difficult and
critical times is keeping well peaceful
and content I want to offer for a few
minutes some reflections on how to
respond to the coronavirus crisis and
the first thing that has to be stated
and said we should be very very diligent
and scrupulous in observing the advice
given to us by the medical professionals
they have our best interest in mind and
even though some of the advice they give
might be difficult to follow but in
order to prevent the spread of the virus
we have to adhere very diligently very
conscientiously to their words of advice
the virus can spread very rapidly and
very widely if we are careless but if we
are careful and diligent then we can
gradually flatten the curve of the virus
that means a set of the virus increasing
shortly like this the virus will
increase gradually and slowly and then
the expansion rate of the virus will
flatten off and hopefully will drop
until the virus vanishes the virus
spreads not in a linear progression but
it spreads virally that is exponentially
from one person it could spread to three
from three to nine from nine to 27 and
so on and so we have to follow the
advice of the medical professionals in
order to curb to stop the spread of the
virus
and some of the main points that the
medical professionals teach us the first
is what is called social distancing
which means that we have to keep a
physical distance from other people the
natural tendency of the human mind is
for people to mix together to come close
together to shake hands when we meet to
hug to speak together intimately to
gather together in groups but if we
happen that way then we're going to
become agents for picking up the virus
ourselves and spreading it to others and
so to avoid that we have to observe
social distancing to keep a distance
from others not to join in group
activities not to go out to public the
public domain but to remain to the best
of our ability to remain at home to
remain in our room the second principle
which is taught by the medical
professionals is to frequently wash
one's hands and to wash them with soap
the reason we have to use soap is
because soap breaks up and destroys the
virus just washing with water is not
sufficient
so you soap and rub the hands together
to create a lather and rub them for
about 20 seconds before rinsing off the
hands so in following the advice of the
professionals the medical professionals
we're taking care firstly of ourselves
but by taking care of ourselves we're
also taking care of others we are
protecting ourselves from picking up the
virus and by avoiding the virus
ourselves we protect others because we
don't become a channel a vector for
spreading the virus to others
so it might seem that taking care of
ourselves is an act of selfishness but
actually this is a true act of
compassion a way to protect others and
there's a sutra spoken by the Buddha
which illustrates this in this Sutra
it's occurs in the Satipaṭṭhāna-saṃyuttaṃ
(Sedaka Sutta) it relates a story of two
acrobats who come to a town one is the
master the other is the disciple so they
come to the town and they set up the
pole the acrobatic pole and then the
master says to his disciple climb on my
shoulders the disciple climbs up on her
shoulders
then the master says you protect me and
I will protect you and then that way
protecting each other we can perform our
feats you'll get down safely from the
pole and we'll make some money but the
disciple says to the master master
that's not the right way to do it rather
you protect yourself I will protect
myself and when we are each protecting
ourselves then we will be safe and
secure in that way we can perform our
feats I'll get down safely and we will
make our living and then the Buddha said
the advice given by the disciple that is
the correct way to perform the acrobatic
feet so the buddha applying this to our
everyday life he says in the same way
protect yourself and by protecting
yourself you'll also protect others and
by protecting others
you also protect yourself and so by
taking care of ourselves properly we'll
protect our family members of our
community members of our
city or town and people throughout the
country now when we face this virus face
this epidemic
many people get overcome by fear by
worried by and even by anxiety even by a
mood of panic so how are we going to
deal with this crisis in terms of the
Dhamma how are we going to apply to
apply the Dharma to help us overcome our
fear or worry or concern and live in
peace and equanimity I want to mention
three different approaches each approach
will be more appropriate for people of a
different temperament one approach is
based on faith and devotion another
approach on mindfulness and
concentration of Samadhi and the third
approach is based on wisdom and insight
of course all three factors should be
interwoven faith mindfulness and wisdom
but different people will place emphasis
on different approaches so for those who
incline to faith and devotion a way to
keep the mind strong calm and joyful is
to call to mind the excellent qualities
the virtues of the objects of our faith
that is the truth the three jewels the
triple gem so he called to mind the
Buddha as they all enlightened one the
perfectly enlightened one the boundless
wisdom and great compassion we call to
mind the Dharma as the path of practice
the way that leads to liberation and
enlightenment and we call to mind the
Sangha this can be the community of the
liberated aura Hut's or the community of
the pure compassionate Bodhi
sathya's we bring them to mind and think
of their purity their wisdom their
compassion their practice and their vows
and so when we let the minds well on the
three jewels and you could choose any of
the jewels that you prefer Buddha Dharma
or Sangha this will give rise to a
feeling an inner feeling of trust of
confidence of quiet joy and of inner
strength which will help us keep calm
and peaceful in this tough time of crisis
the second approach emphasizes
mindfulness leading to greater inner
calm and concentration so if this
approach we sit down in our meditation
seat and we set up my mindfulness first
the mindfulness of the whole body
feeling the body as a whole you can scan
the body and feel the sensations of the
body you can feel the touch of your
buttocks against the seat the legs on
the ground or the feet on the ground and
then you can turn your attention to the
breath and be mindful when breathing in
be mindful of the in-breath when
breathing out be mindful of the
out-breath and when thoughts arise
thoughts of worry thoughts of fear
thoughts of planning thoughts of anger
or thoughts of resentment whatever
thoughts arise you can just briefly note
that God let the thought come we'll let
it go drop the thought and bring the
mind back to the main object coming back
to the feeling of the body and then
moving from the body back to the breath
and if any of these feelings of fear
worry anxiety becomes very strong then
you can drop the breath and just focus
on the thought itself turning the
thought into an object or you can focus
on the sensations in the body as that
thought is running through the mind
feeling the tightness the clenching the
tension in the body and then using your
mind's you can relax the tension of the
body and when you feel ready then you
can bring the mind back to the breath
and in this way
whatever happens outwardly you remain
centered inwardly calm peaceful with
equanimity the third approach is to use
wisdom or wise reflection —yoniso manasikāra
as a way as a way to deal with
the crisis brought on by the virus and
so with why is reflection we consider
that the virus is something of a teacher
teaching us the real nature of life
usually in our day to day life we always
continue our activities on the tacit
assumption that everything will go on
normally without any any disruption we
think we're always safe and secure but
what the Buddha teaches is that
underneath the peaceful surface of our
everyday life there are always dangers
hiding in the background and so now with
the virus these dangers have come out
from hiding into the open and so some of
the themes that the Buddha teaches his
disciples for daily reflection is to
reflect I am subject to old age I have
not escaped from old age
I am subject to illness I have not
escaped illness I am subject to death
I have not escaped death so we've picked
up this physical body at our birth we've
come into this world and having a body
living in this world
we're subject to aging subject to
illness subject to death and now as this
virus spreads we are facing the
realities particularly of illness and
the potential for death and so we have
to keep our mind strong have to keep the
mind prepared a fourth topic that the
Buddha teaches for reflection is that I
must be parted and separated from
everyone that I love so even if we
continue to live if we don't die
ourselves our loved ones our relatives
our friends are also subject to death so
they might pass away before we do and if
we are not inwardly prepared then when
they pass away we become overcome by
grief and by misery even by depression
but if we consider this theme reflect on
this theme when our loved ones fall ill
and pass away and of course we feel
sorrow what we can maintain our strength
or tranquility through that sorrow and
come out stronger ready to face the
challenges of life the fifth theme that
the Buddha teaches is that when we pass
away all that we take with us when we
move on to the next life is our Karma
the legacy of our good deeds and our bad
deeds and so if we bring this theme to
mind we say that we should right now
begin to perform good
NEADS especially by giving in charity to
organizations and are helping to address
the crisis of the virus to medical
organizations health care organizations
food distribution centers and so forth
that are helping people affected by the
virus and so we can choose whatever
approach we prefer the approach of faith
and devotion the approach of mindfulness
and concentration the approach of wisdom
of wise reflection in order to keep our
mind calm tranquil inwardly strong able
to face the crisis with courage and when
we have a calm strong courageous mind
that will boost the immune system so
that we become less vulnerable to the
virus if we're exposed to this but I
hope that everybody who listens to this
recording will be safe and secure be
peaceful and happy and that in no short
time in no long time the medical
profession will find the vaccine that
can eliminate the virus and so we can
return to our everyday life and so I
want to end this little series of
reflections by reciting some verses of
blessing calling upon the spiritual
power of the three jewels to protect
everybody who listens so these are
verses in the ancient pali language
wishing that you all be free from
illness that you enjoy a long lifespan
and that by the blessings of the buddha
the dhamma and the sangha and with the
protection of the deities you'll all be
safe and healthy
Sabbītiyo (May all calamities be avoided,)
vivajjantu Sabba-rogo vinassatu, Mā( may all diseases disappear)
te bhavatvantarāyo Sukhī dīghāyuko bhava (may there be no obstacle[s] for you, [and may] you be happy and have long life.)
Bhavatu sabba-maṅgalaṁ Rakkhantu (May all blessings be [yours],)
sabba-devatā, Sabba-buddhānubhāvena (may all the deities protect [you]; by the power of all the Buddhas,)
Sadā sotthi bhavantu te. (may you have well-being always.)
Bhavatu sabba-maṅgalaṁ Rakkhantu (May all blessings be [yours])
sabba-devatā, Sabba-dhammānubhāvena Sadā sotthi (, may all the deities protect [you]; (by the power of all the Dhammas, may you have well-being always.)
bhavantu te. Bhavatu sabba-maṅgalaṁ (May all blessings be [yours],)
Rakkhantu sabba-devatā, Sabba-saṅghānubhā (may all the deities protect [you]. by the power of all the Saṅghas,)
vena Sadā sotthi bhavantu te ( may you have well-being always.). thank you
for listening and may you all be well
may you all be safe may you all be
healthy and may we all come out from
this crisis from this epidemic stronger
with a greater sense of personal
responsibility for each other with
hearts full of loving-kindness and
compassion determined to work to create
a community a society a world in which
everyone can flourish and realize their
virtuous aspirations