Namo tassa bhagavato arahato
sammāsambuddhassa good morning everybody I'm
recording this little talk from Swami
and monastery in Carmel New York and it
is today is the morning of March 29th
I made a recording of some reflections
on the coronavirus about a week ago on
March 23rd and so now six more days have
gone by and according to the statistics
that I gathered this morning at present
globally there have been six hundred and
sixty thousand cases of reported
infections with the virus and thirty
thousand reported deaths from the virus
and I have to emphasize that these are
reported or recorded cases there can be
many more cases of people infected which
have not been reported confirmed and
recorded here in the United States
according to the figures I collected
they've been approximately a hundred
twenty thousand infections and two
thousand deaths the number of deaths has
doubled over the past couple of days in
the New York area in new actually in New
York City there have been 52,000 cases
of infection reported and approximately
800 deaths
the country with the greatest number of
deaths so far is Italy which has
recorded 10,000 deaths and when we look
at these figures and we could see how
cases of infection are spreading all
around us even amongst people who were
famous prominent powerful eminent people
who never thought they would be infected
then our own minds might be always
constantly overcome by fear by worry by
anxiety what should happen if I get
infected and this fear is quite
justified it's not in a rational fear
because the virus spreads almost an
invisible imperceptible ways and though
there are measures that we can adopt
measures that are recommended by the
various institutes of health by the
medical professionals methods that we
can adopt to protect ourselves from
infection by the virus no method is
absolutely foolproof
there's no in vulnerably we can't
guarantee that we'll be completely
invulnerable to the virus in fact this
past week one day this past week while I
was taking a walk around the monastery
I saw a parcel that the post had thrown
over the gate and I picked up that
parcel and brought it to the person for
whom it was intended and after I did
that suddenly the fear came over me I
picked up the parcel with my bare hands
that what if that parcel had been
infected with the virus what if it was
carrying the virus perhaps I too would
have been infected without knowing it
and I expected any day I would start to
get symptoms from the virus and so they
came over me as fear even almost some
degree of panic but here I am in
relatively secluded conditions I get
infected with the virus and maybe if the
virus the disease starts to advanced
very quickly within a day or two the
obituary obituary for bhikkhu bodhi
appears on some of the websites the
buddhist websites fortunately that
hasn't happened and I haven't felt any
symptoms but that was a very real
possibility okay so I want to give some
thought some reflections about how do we
deal with fear the fear and anxiety that
can arise over the thought I might pick
up the virus or maybe I'm feeling a
little bit strange today maybe I have
picked up the virus and maybe it's
starting to germinate and to spread
within my system as I said this can be a
very real fear and though there are some
people who say that one shouldn't
experience any fear at all I think it's
quite legitimate that one feels an
initial wave of fear and worry and
concern when if one starts to feel
symptoms or when one considers the
possibility that one might pick up the
infection what one has to do is to
prevent the fear that arises from
overpowering the mind and from
incapacitating the mind and so one of
the remedies the means for dealing with
the fear that might arise is to settle
down and not feel immediately compelled
to go into action when fear arises but
first settle down and reflect back upon
oneself using that great Buddhist
function called mindfulness so if fear
arises one could go to one's accustom
meditation seat and just sit down not
resolving on a long meditation but just
resolving to sit quietly for five
minutes 10 minutes
just to settle the mind and to
experience the body more clearly and
more intimately because it can be that
the unusual feelings that what is
experiencing in the body different mood
different sensations in the body that
these are things which are being
manufactured by the mind out of that
deeply embedded fear and worry about
picking up the virus so settle down and
get a sense of the body what I call a
global a total istic sense of the body
and then raise the question am I really
experiencing something different
or is this just something which is being
conjured up by my imagination and then
if one can confirm that one is feeling
something different in the body once
you'd check these strange sensations the
unusual sensations one is experiencing
check them against the list of these
symptoms of the Cova virus or the corona
virus of the Covey's illness to say
whether they correspond because for
example if you are getting a sore throat
and your nose is running and you're
blowing into the handkerchief it's very
unlikely that that is the coal feed
illness because the way I've seen it on
the websites the signs the typical signs
of the Coheed illness would be a dry
cough and tightness or constriction in
the lungs but don't take my word for it
but go to one of the websites probably
the best source with for Americans would
be the website of the Center for Disease
Control CDC or John Hopkins University
or any of the other there are many many
websites which are now listing the
symptoms
of the co vide 19 and so if your
symptoms don't correspond to those on
the list then you can relax you might
have simple simply a cold or a ordinary
case of the flu and in that case take
the appropriate remedies for a cold or a
flu if your symptoms correspond to those
of the Co vide virus and you should
follow the advice given on the websites
the health websites I'm not a health
specialist so I'm not going to recommend
anything but what I could do as a
buddhist as a buddhist monk this give
some advice on how to deal with the fear
and worry that arise within the mind and
what one wants to do is keep i would
call this a healthy dose of fear taking
the sense or turning that fear into
concern and the motivation to take the
right course of action but not letting
the fear intensify duplicate multiply
proliferate and overwhelm the fear so
that one becomes paralyzed with fear
incapacitated blocked and impeded from
taking effective action when doesn't
want the fear to become something which
immobilizes the mind so for those who
are following the Buddha Dharma but I
would recommend is a method which is
suggested in a suitor a discourse of the
Buddha that occurs in the Sun Mutiny kya
the connected discourses and this occurs
in the chapter it's chapter 11 of the
Samyukta nakiya
is called the sakura-san yuta the
connected discourses with Saku Saku is
the ruler of the tava things of Davis
and this is suta number 3
call the DA jogger suta the crest of the
standard that's a crest that is placed
on the banner that whirring factions
factions of warriors would carry into
battle against their opponents and in
the suitor the Buddha has described a
battle that takes place we call between
the davises the good deities and the
Asura's who are the demons the anti gods
and when this battle takes place
sokka the king of the gods tells the
Devas that when you are engaged in this
battle if fear or anxiety should arise
in you then you should look up at the
crest on the top of my banner and when
you look up at that crest and you'll say
that I am present leading the battle and
then your fear worry and anxiety will be
abandoned and then he mentions some
other ways that the deities could dispel
their fear then he applies this to the
case of the monks who go into the forest
or to a deserted place to practice
meditation and sometimes when they go
all alone into these isolated places a
dark forest fear and anxiety can arise
in them with the thought that there
might be demons in this forest of wild
animals or malicious spirits of some
sort and so then the Buddha says when
that happens then you should call to
mind myself the Buddha himself calling
to mind that I the Buddha is one who is
perfectly enlightened the blessed one
the fully enlightened one and when you
think about me
then your fear terror and anxiety will
be dispersed if you don't think of me
then you can think of the Dhamma call to
mind the Dhamma which is well expounded
directly visible immediate something to
be personally realized by the wise and
if you don't think of me
you don't think of the Dhamma think of the
Sangha the community of noble disciples
think of how the community of disciples
is endowed with great virtues of wisdom
compassion purity patience diligence and
so forth and then with reverence and
veneration bringing to mind the Sangha
of noble disciples the great field of
merit for the world your fear and worry
and anxiety will be dispelled so that is
the advice that the Buddha gives to
monks who have gone into seclusion to
practice meditation and we ourselves can
use these reflections these
contemplations in order to allay to
dispel our own obsessive fear in anxiety
so you can bring to mind the figure of
the Buddha you can use an image or
picture of the Buddha bring it to mind
and think I have taken refuge in the
Buddha the perfectly enlightened one the
one endowed with boundless wisdom and
great compassion or you can call to mind
the Dhamma the well expounded path
leading to perfect wisdom and to
liberation or call to mind the Sangha
the community of great era Hut's
including such monks as Sāriputta
Moggallāna, Mahākassapa, Ānanda, and so
forth and think of the virtues of the
discipline
samadhi and wisdom and liberation of
those great monks and that will help
your fear and anxiety to be dispelled I
want to emphasize that doing these
reflections these contemplations is not
a substitute for obtaining proper
medical advice it's not an alternative
to consulting with the healthcare
professionals but rather it's a way of
temporarily alleviating relieving the
fear and worry that might arise in your
mind and so once you dispel and quiet
down this fear worry and anxiety then
you should take the action recommended
by the health experts and I will try to
attach to this recording some of the
websites that you could turn to for
professional advice so I want to end by
expressing my wish my hope that all of
you who are listening will be free from
illness free from affliction free from
the coronavirus and from every other
kind of illness but if you should be
infected by the virus
I give my blessings that you
will be quickly recover from the illness
regain your strength and your health and
in any case I hope that all of you will
be free from what I call the obsessive
and incapacitating type of fear but you
should use that healthy degree of fear
to take proper precautions as
recommended by the health experts to
protect yourself as well as possible
from infection by the virus so let me
end with extending the blessings of the
three jewels to all of you
Sabbītiyo vivajjantu Sabba-rogo vinassatu (May all calamities be avoided, may all diseases disappear,)
Mā te bhavatvantarāyo Sukhī dīghāyuko bhava. (may there be no obstacle[s] for you, [and may] you be happy and have long life.)
Bhavatu sabba-maṅgalaṁ Rakkhantu sabba-devatā (May all blessings be [yours], may all the deities protect [you])
Sabba-buddhānubhāvena Sadā sotthi bhavantu te. (by the power of all the Buddhas, may you have well-being always.)
Bhavatu sabba-maṅgalaṁ Rakkhantu sabba-devatā
(May all blessings be [yours], may all the deities protect [you])
Sabba-dhammānubhāvena Sadā sotthi bhavantu te. (by the power of all the Dhammas, may you have well-being always.)
Bhavatu sabba-maṅgalaṁ Rakkhantu sabba-devatā (May all blessings be [yours], may all the deities protect [you])
Sabba-saṅghānubhāvena Sadā sotthi bhavantu te.
(by the power of all the Saṅghas, may you have well-being always.) Sādhu (Being well)
sādhu, sādhu (Being well, Being well)
sādhu! (Being well!)